Let me begin with four words
دعوني أبدأ بأربع كلمات
that will provide the context for this week,
ستشكل السياق لهذا الأسبوع،
four words that will come to define
أربع كلمات ستكون تعريفا
this century.
لهذا القرن.
Here they are:
ها هي ذي:
The Earth is full.
الأرض ممتلئة.
It's full of us, it's full of our stuff,
إنها ممتلئة بنا، وممتلئة بأغراضنا،
full of our waste, full of our demands.
ممتلئة بفضلاتنا وممتلئة بمتطلباتنا.
Yes, we are a brilliant and creative species,
نعم، نحن صنف مبدع وعبقري،
but we've created a little too much stuff --
لكننا قد صنعنا أكثر من اللازم بقليل من الأشياء --
so much that our economy is now bigger
أكثر بحيث أن اقتصادنا الآن أكبر
than its host, our planet.
من مضيفنا، كوكبنا.
This is not a philosophical statement,
هذا ليس كلاما فلسفيا،
this is just science
هذا فقط علم
based in physics,
يعتمد على الفيزياء،
chemistry and biology.
والكيمياء وعلم الأحياء.
There are many science-based analyses of this,
هناك الكثير من التحليلات العلمية لهذا،
but they all draw the same conclusion --
لكنها جميعا تخلص إلى نفس الشيء --
that we're living beyond our means.
أننا نعيش خارج إمكانياتنا.
The eminent scientists of the Global Footprint Network, for example,
العلماء البارزون من شبكة فووتبرينت العالمية، على سبيل المثال،
calculate that we need about 1.5 Earths
يعتقدون أننا نحتاج إلى حوالي الأرض والنصف
to sustain this economy.
للحفاظ على الإقتصاد.
In other words,
بعبارة أخرى،
to keep operating at our current level,
لنبقى حيويين في مستوانا الحالي،
we need 50 percent more Earth than we've got.
نحتاج 50 في المئة من الأرض أكثر مما لدينا.
In financial terms,
من الناحية المالية،
this would be like always spending 50 percent more than you earn,
هذا قد يكون مثل صرف 50 في المئة أكثر مما تجنيه،
going further into debt every year.
متجها نحو المديونية كل سنة.
But of course, you can't borrow natural resources,
لكن بالطبع، لا يمكنك إقتراض الموارد الطبيعية،
so we're burning through our capital,
وبالتالي فنحن نحرق رأسمالنا استهلاكا،
or stealing from the future.
أو نسرق من المستقبل.
So when I say full, I mean really full --
وبالتالي حين أقول ممتلئة، أقصد ممتلئة حقا --
well past any margin for error,
في ما يتعدى أي هامش خطأ،
well past any dispute
متجازوة أي خلافات
about methodology.
حول المنهجية.
What this means is our economy is unsustainable.
ما يعنيه هذا أن اقتصادنا غير مستدام.
I'm not saying it's not nice or pleasant
لست أقول أنه ليس جيد أو حسن
or that it's bad for polar bears or forests,
أو أنه سيء بالنسبة للدببة القطبية والغابات،
though it certainly is.
مع أنه بالتأكيد كذلك.
What I'm saying
ما أقوله
is our approach is simply unsustainable.
هو أن مقاربتنا هي بكل بساطة غير مستدامة.
In other words, thanks to those pesky laws of physics,
بعبارة أخرى، بفضل قوانين الفيزياء المزعجة تلك،
when things aren't sustainable, they stop.
حين لا تكون الأشياء مستدامة، تتوقف.
But that's not possible, you might think.
لكنكم قد تظنون أن ذلك غير ممكن.
We can't stop economic growth.
لا نستطيع إيقاف النمو الإقتصادي.
Because that's what will stop: economic growth.
لأن ذلك ما سيتوقف: النمو الإقتصادي.
It will stop because of the end of trade resources.
سيتوقف لأنها ستكون نهاية الموارد التجارية.
It will stop because of the growing demand of us
سيتوقف بسبب طلبنا المتزايد
on all the resources, all the capacity,
على الموارد وكل السعات
all the systems of the Earth,
وكل الأنظمة على الأرض،
which is now having economic damage.
والتي تعرف الآن ضررا اقتصاديا.
When we think about economic growth stopping,
حين نفكر في توقيف النمو الإقتصادي،
we go, "That's not possible,"
نقول، "ذلك غير ممكن،"
because economic growth is so essential to our society
لأن النمو الإقتصادي مهم جدا لمجتمعنا
that is is rarely questioned.
نادرا ما يتم التساؤل بخصوص ذلك.
Although growth has certainly delivered many benefits,
مع أن النمو قد أفرز مزايا كثيرة،
it is an idea so essential
إنه فكرة أساسية جدا
that we tend not to understand
لا نفهمها غالبا
the possibility of it not being around.
إمكانية ألا يبقى هناك نمو.
Even though it has delivered many benefits,
مع أنه أفرز إيجابيات كثيرة،
it is based on a crazy idea --
فهو يعتمد على فكرة جنونية --
the crazy idea being
كون
that we can have infinite growth
أنه يمكننا التوفر على نمو لا نهائي
on a finite planet.
على كوكب محدود.
And I'm here to tell you the emperor has no clothes.
وأنا هنا لأخبركم أن الإمبراطور لا يلبس ثيابا.
That the crazy idea is just that,
أن الفكرة الجنونية فقط أنها،
it is crazy,
جنونية،
and with the Earth full, it's game over.
ومع كون الأرض مليئة، فإن تلك نهاية اللعبة.
Come on, you're thinking.
بالله عليكم، أنتم تفكرون.
That's not possible.
ذلك غير ممكن.
Technology is amazing. People are innovative.
التكنولوجيا رائعة. والناس مبدعون.
There are so many ways we can improve the way we do things.
هناك الكثير من الطرق للتحسين من الطريقة التي نقوم بها بالأشياء.
We can surely sort this out.
نستطيع بالتأكيد حل المشكلة.
That's all true.
كل ذلك صحيح.
Well, it's mostly true.
حسنا، معظمه صحيح.
We are certainly amazing,
نحن مذهلون بحق،
and we regularly solve complex problems
ونحل المشاكل المعقدة بانتظام
with amazing creativity.
بإبداعية مذهلة.
So if our problem
وبالتالي إن كانت مشكلتنا
was to get the human economy down
هي خفض الإقتصاد البشري
from 150 percent to 100 percent of the Earth's capacity,
من 150 في المئة إلى 100 في المئة من إمكانيات الأرض،
we could do that.
نستطيع القيام بذلك.
The problem is we're just warming up
المشكلة هي أننا فقط في مرحلة تسخين
this growth engine.
محرك النمو هذا.
We plan to take this highly-stressed economy
نخطط لأخذ هذا الإقتصاد العالي الضغط
and make it twice as big
وجعله أكبر بمرتين
and then make it four times as big --
ومن ثم جعله أكبر بأربع مرات --
not in some distant future,
ليس في مستقبل بعيد،
but in less than 40 years,
لكن في أقل من 40 سنة،
in the life time of most of you.
في مدى حياة معظمكم.
China plans to be there in just 20 years.
تخطط الصين أن تكون هناك في غضون 20 سنة فقط.
The only problem with this plan
المشكلة الوحيد في هذه الخطة
is that it's not possible.
هو أنها غير ممكنة.
In response, some people argue,
البعض يرد مجادلا،
but we need growth, we need it to solve poverty.
لكننا نحتاج إلى النمو، نحتاجه لحل مشكل الفقر.
We need it to develop technology.
نحتاجه لتطوير التكنولوجيا.
We need it to keep social stability.
نحتاجه للحفاظ على الأمن الإجتماعي.
I find this argument fascinating,
أجد هذا الجدال فاتنا،
as though we can kind of bend the rules of physics
وكأننا نستطيع أن نلوي قوانين الفيزياء
to suit our needs.
لتوافق احتياجاتنا.
It's like the Earth doesn't care what we need.
وكأن الأرض لا تهتم لما نحتاجه.
Mother nature doesn't negotiate;
الطبيعة الأم لا تتفاوض؛
she just sets rules and describes consequences.
تقوم فقط بوضع القواعد وتصف العواقب.
And these are not esoteric limits.
وتلك ليست حدودا محصورة بفئة معينة.
This is about food and water, soil and climate,
يتعلق الأمر بالماء والغذاء والتربة والمناخ،
the basic practical and economic foundations
الأسس الإقتصادية العملية الأساسية
of our lives.
لحياتنا.
So the idea that we can smoothly transition
وبالتالي ففكرة أننا نستطيع الإنتقال بسلاسة
to a highly-efficient,
إلى إقتصاد عالي الكفاءة
solar-powered, knowledge-based economy
يعمل بالطاقة الشمسية ويعتمد على المعرفة
transformed by science and technology
منتقلين بالعلم والتكنولوجيا
so that nine billion people
بحيث أن تسعة مليارات شخص
can live in 2050
يستطيعون العيش سنة 2050
a life of abundance and digital downloads
حياة من الوفرة والتحميلات الرقمية
is a delusion.
هي وهم.
It's not that it's not possible to feed, clothe and house us all
لا يعني ذلك أنه من المستحيل تغذية وإيواء جميعنا
and have us live decent lives.
وجعلنا نعيش حياة كريمة.
It certainly is.
إنها بالفعل كذلك.
But the idea that we can gently grow there
لكن فكرة أنه يمكننا أن نصل بنمونا بلطف إلى هناك
with a few minor hiccups
مع بضع عثرات بسيطة
is just wrong,
هي فقط خاطئة،
and it's dangerously wrong,
وهي خاطئة بشكل خطير،
because it means we're not getting ready
لأنها تعني أننا لا نستعد
for what's really going to happen.
لما سيحدث حقا.
See what happens when you operate a system
وما يحدث حين تشغل نظاما
past its limits
متجاوزا حدوده
and then keep on going
ونستمر في ذلك
at an ever-accelerating rate
في معدل تسارعي مستمر
is that the system stops working and breaks down.
هو أن النظام يتوقف عن العمل ويصاب بالعطل.
And that's what will happen to us.
وهذا ما سيحدث لنا.
Many of you will be thinking,
الكثير منكم قد يفكرون،
but surely we can still stop this.
لكننا لا نزال نستطيع بالتأكيد إيقاف هذا.
If it's that bad, we'll react.
إن كان الأمر بذلك السوء، سنتفاعل.
Let's just think through that idea.
دعونا فقط نتمعن في تلك الفكرة.
Now we've had
قد وصلنا الآن
50 years of warnings.
إلى 50 سنة من التحذيرات.
We've had science proving
قد أثبت لنا العلم
the urgency of change.
اهمية الاستعجال بمبادرات التغير
We've had economic analysis pointing out
لدينا تحليلات إقتصادية تبين
that, not only can we afford it,
أنه، ليس فقط أننا لا نستطيع تحمل ذلك،
it's cheaper to act early.
بل أنه من الأرخص التحرك مبكرا.
And yet, the reality is
ومع ذلك، الحقيقة أنه
we've done pretty much nothing to change course.
لم نقم بأي شيء أبدا لتغيير المسار.
We're not even slowing down.
لسنا نتباطىء حتى.
Last year on climate, for example,
في السنة الماضية في المناخ، على سبيل المثال،
we had the highest global emissions ever.
كان لدينا أعلى معدل من الانبعاث على الإطلاق.
The story on food, on water, on soil, on climate
قصة الغذاء والماء والتربة والمناخ
is all much the same.
هي نفسها تماما.
I actually don't say this in despair.
لست أقول هذا في الواقع بدافع اليأس.
I've done my grieving about the loss.
حزنت لما فيه الكفاية على الخسارة.
I accept where we are.
أتقبل أين نحن.
It is sad,
إنه محزن،
but it is what it is.
لكنه ما هو عليه.
But it is also time
لكن حان كذلك الوقت
that we ended our denial
لننهي نكراننا
and recognized
ونعترف
that we're not acting, we're not close to acting
أننا لسنا نعمل، ولسنا حتى قريبين من العمل
and we're not going to act
ولسنا مقبلين على العمل
until this crisis hits the economy.
حتى تضرب هذه الأزمة الإقتصاد.
And that's why the end of growth
ولذلك فإن نهاية النمو
is the central issue
هو المشكلة الأساسية
and the event that we need to get ready for.
والحدث الذي نحتاج إلى التحضير له.
So when does this transition begin?
إذن متى يبدأ هذا التحول؟
When does this breakdown begin?
متى يبدأ هذا الانهيار؟
In my view, it is well underway.
في نظري، إنه يجري حاليا.
I know most people don't see it that way.
أعرف أن معظمكم لا يرى الأمر على هذا الشكل.
We tend to look at the world,
نميل إلى النظر إلى العالم،
not as the integrated system that it is,
ليس كالنظام المتكامل الذي هو عليه،
but as a series of individual issues.
لكن كسلسلة من المشاكل المنفردة.
We see the Occupy protests,
نرى احتجاجات الاحتلال،
we see spiraling debt crises,
نرى أزمات الديون المتصاعدة،
we see growing inequality,
نرى التباين المتزايد
we see money's influence on politics,
نرى تأثير المال على السياسة،
we see resource constraint, food and oil prices.
نرى القيود على الموارد، أسعار النفط والغذاء.
But we see, mistakenly, each of these issues
لكننا نرى، بطريقة خاطئة، كل واحد من هذه المشاكل
as individual problems to be solved.
كمشاكل فردية ينبغي حلها.
In fact, it's the system
في الواقع، إنه النظام
in the painful process of breaking down --
في سيره المؤلم نحو الانهيار --
our system, of debt-fueled economic growth,
نظامنا، للنمو الإقتصادي الذي تغذيه الديون،
of ineffective democracy,
للديموقراطية عديمة الفاعلية،
of overloading planet Earth,
للحمولة الزائدة على الأرض،
is eating itself alive.
نظام يأكل نفسه حيا.
I could give you countless studies
أستطيع إعطائكم ما لا يعد من الدراسات
and evidence to prove this,
والأدلة لإثبات هذا،
but I won't because, if you want to see it,
لكنني لن أفعل لأنه إن أردتم أن تروا ذلك،
that evidence is all around you.
فإن الأدلة كلها حولكم.
I want to talk to you about fear.
أريد أن أحدثكم عن الخوف.
I want to do so because, in my view,
أريد القيام بذلك لأنه في نظري،
the most important issue we face
الإشكال الأهم الذي نواجهه
is how we respond
هو كيف نجيب
to this question.
على هذا السؤال.
The crisis is now inevitable.
الأزمة الأن حتمية.
This issue is, how will we react?
المشكلة هي، كيف سنتفاعل؟
Of course, we can't know what will happen.
بالطبع، لن يمكننا معرفة ما الذي سيحدث.
The future is inherently uncertain.
المستقبل غير مؤكد بطبعه.
But let's just think through what the science is telling us
لكن دعونا فقط نتمعن فيما يخبرنا العلم
is likely to happen.
أنه من المرجح حدوثه.
Imagine our economy
تخيلوا اقتصادنا
when the carbon bubble bursts,
حين تنفجر أزمة الكربون
when the financial markets recognize
حين تعترف الأسواق المالية
that, to have any hope
أنه، ليكون لدينا أدنى أمل
of preventing the climate spiraling out of control,
في حماية المناخ من الخروج عن السيطرة،
the oil and coal industries are finished.
يجب أن تتوقف صناعات الفحم و النفط
Imagine China, India and Pakistan going to war
تخيلوا إن ذهبت الصين والهند وباكستان إلى الحرب
as climate impacts
كآثار مناخية
generate conflict over food and water.
تولد الصراعات على الماء والغذاء.
Imagine the Middle East without oil income,
تخيلوا الشرق الأوسط من دون مداخيل النفط،
but with collapsing governments.
لكن مع حكومات منهارة.
Imagine our highly-tuned, just-in-time food industry
تخيلوا صناعة الغذاء لدينا الفورية والمضبوطة بدقة
and our highly-stressed agricultural system failing
ونظامنا الزراعي العالي التوتر إذ إنهار
and supermarket shelves emptying.
ورفوف الأسواق الممتازة إذ تصير فارغة.
Imagine 30 percent unemployment in America
تخيلوا نسبة 30 في المئة من البطالة في أمريكا
as the global economy is gripped
والإقتصاد العالمي تحت سيطرة
by fear and uncertainty.
الخوف والشكوك.
Now imagine what that means for you,
الآن تخيلوا ما الذي يعنيه ذلك بالنسبة لكم،
your family, your friends,
وعائلاتكم وأصدقائكم،
your personal financial security.
وأمنكم المالي الشخصي.
Imagine what it means
تخيلوا ما يعنيه
for your personal security
لأمنكم الخاص
as a heavily armed civilian population
وشعب مدجج بالسلاح
gets angrier and angrier
يزداد غضبا على غضب
about why this was allowed to happen.
حول السبب الذي سمح لهذا بالحصول.
Imagine what you'll tell your children
تخيلوا ماذا ستخبرون به أطفالكم
when they ask you,
حين يسألونكم،
"So, in 2012, Mom and Dad,
"حسنا، أبي وأمي، كيف كانت
what was it like
سنة 2012
when you'd had the hottest decade on record
حين كنتم في أكثر عقد حرارة في التاريخ
for the third decade in a row,
للسنة الثالثة على التوالي،
when every scientific body in the world was saying
حين كانت كل هيئة علمية في العالم تقول
you've got a major problem,
أنه لدينا مشكلة ضخم،ة
when the oceans were acidifying,
حين كانت المحيطات تتحمض،
when oil and food prices were spiking,
حين كانت أسعار الغذاء والنفط تتزايد فجأة،
when they were rioting in the streets of London
حين كان هناك ثوار في شوارع لندن
and occupying Wall Street?
ومحتلون في وول ستريت؟
When the system was so clearly breaking down, Mom and Dad,
حين كان النظام ينهار بوضوح، أبي وأمي،
what did you do, what were you thinking?"
ما الذي قمتم به، ما الذي كنتم تفكرون فيه؟"
So how do you feel
إذن كيف تشعرون
when the lights go out
حين تنطفئ الأضواء
on the global economy in your mind,
على الإقتصاد العالمي في دماغكم،
when your assumptions about the future
حين يتبخر افتراضكم
fade away
بخصوص المستقبل
and something very different emerges?
ويظهر شيء مختلف تماما؟
Just take a moment
توقفوا للحظة فقط
and take a breath
وخذوا نفسا
and think, what do you feel
وفكروا كيف تشعرون
at this point?
الآن؟
Perhaps denial.
ربما نكران.
Perhaps anger.
ربما غضب.
Maybe fear.
ربما خوف.
Of course, we can't know what's going to happen
بالطبع، لا يمكننا معرفة ما الذي سيحصل
and we have to live with uncertainty.
وعلينا أن نعيش مع الشك.
But when we think about the kind of possibilities I paint,
لكن حين نفكر في نوع الاحتمالات التي أرسمها،
we should feel a bit of fear.
علينا أن نحس بنوع من الخوف.
We are in danger, all of us,
نحن في خطر، جميعنا،
and we've evolved to respond to danger with fear
وقد تطورنا للتجاوب مع الخطر والخوف
to motivate a powerful response,
لتحفيز رد قوي،
to help us bravely face a threat.
لمساعدتنا على مواجهة التهديد بشجاعة.
But this time it's not a tiger at the cave mouth.
لكن هذه المرة ليس الخطر نمرا على باب الكهف.
You can't see the danger at your door.
لا يمكنك أن ترى الخطر على بابك.
But if you look,
لكن حين تنظر،
you can see it at the door of your civilization.
يمكنك أن تراه على باب حضارتك.
That's why we need to feel our response now while the lights are still on,
لهذا نحتاج للشعور بالمسؤولية الآن ما دامت الأضواء لا تزال مضاءة،
because if we wait until the crisis takes hold,
لأنه إن انتظرنا حتى تتمكن الأزمة، منا
we may panic and hide.
قد نرتعب ونختبئ.
If we feel it now and think it through,
نشعر بذلك الآن ونتمعن فيه،
we will realize we have nothing to fear
سنتيقن أنه ليس لدينا ما نخافه
but fear itself.
سوى الخوف نفسه.
Yes, things will get ugly, and it will happen soon --
نعم، ستزداد الأمور سوء، وسيحدث هذا قريبا --
certainly in our lifetime --
وبالتأكيد في عمرنا --
but we are more than capable
لكننا أكثر من قادرين
of getting through everything that's coming.
على تجاوز كل ما هو قادم.
You see, those people that have faith
ترون، أولئك الناس الذين يؤمنون
that humans can solve any problem,
بأن الناس يمكنهم حل أي مشكل،
that technology is limitless, that markets can be a force for good,
أن التكنولوجيا لا حدود لها وأن الأسواق يمكنها أن تكون قوة خير
are in fact right.
هم بالفعل محقون.
The only thing they're missing
الأمر الوحيد الذي يفتقدونه
is that it takes a good crisis to get us going.
هو أننا في حاجة إلى أزمة جيدة لتحريكنا.
When we feel fear and we fear loss
حين نحس بالخوف ونخاف من الخسارة
we are capable of quite extraordinary things.
نكون قادرين على أمور استثنائية.
Think about war.
فكروا في الحرب.
After the bombing of Pearl Harbor, it just took four days
بعد تفجير بيرل هاربور، استغرق الأمر أياما
for the government to ban the production of civilian cars
حتى تمنع الحكومة إنتاج السيارات المدنية
and to redirect the auto industry,
وتعيد توجيه صناعة السيارات،
and from there to rationing of food and energy.
وثم من هناك تقنين الغذاء والطاقة.
Think about how a company responds to a bankruptcy threat
فكروا كيف تتجاوب شركة مع تهديد الإفلاس
and how a change that seemed impossible just gets done.
وكيف أن تغييرا بدى مستحيلا حدث بكل بساطة.
Think about how an individual responds
فكروا كيف يتجاوب فرد
to a diagnosis of a life-threatening illness
مع تشخيص مرض يهدد حياته
and how lifestyle changes
وكيف أن تغييرات نمط الحياة
that previously were just too difficult
والتي كانت صعبة جدا من قبل
suddenly become relatively easy.
تصير فجأة سهلة نسبيا.
We are smart, in fact, we really are quite amazing,
نحن أذكياء، في الواقع، نحن في الواقع مذهلون للغاية،
but we do love a good crisis.
لكننا نحب الأزمات الجيدة.
And the good news, this one's a monster.
والأخبار الجيدة أن هذه ستكون وحشا.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
Sure, if we get it wrong,
وبالتأكيد، إن تلقيناها بشكل خاطئ،
we could face the end of this civilization,
قد نواجه نهاية هذه الحضارة،
but if we get it right,
لكن إن تلقيناها بشكل صحيح،
it could be the beginning of civilization instead.
قد تكون بداية حضارة عوضاً عن ذلك.
And how cool would it be
ما مدى روعة ذلك
to tell your grandchildren that you were part of that?
أن تخبر أحفادك أنك كنت جزء من ذلك؟
There's certainly no technical or economic barrier in the way.
ليست هناك بالتأكيد أي حواجز إقتصادية أو تقنية على الطريق.
Scientists like James Hansen tell us
العلماء مثل جيمس هانسن يخبروننا
we may need to eliminate net CO2 emissions from the economy
أنه علينا أن نزيل انبعاث ثنائي أكسيد الكربون من الإقتصاد
in just a few decades.
في غضون عقود قليلة.
I wanted to know what that would take,
أردت معرفة ما الذي قد يتطلبه ذلك،
so I worked with professor Jorgen Randers from Norway
وبالتالي اشتغلت مع البروفيسور يورغن راندرز من النرويج
to find the answer.
لإيجاد الجواب.
We developed a plan called "The One Degree War Plan" --
طورنا خطة تدعى "خطة حرب الدرجة الواحدة" --
so named because of the level of mobilization and focus required.
سميت بذلك بسبب مستوى التجنيد والتركيز المطلوب.
To my surprise,
ولدهشتي،
eliminating net CO2 emissions from the economy in just 20 years
إزالة انبعاث ثنائي أكسيد الكربون من الإقتصاد خلال 20 سنة فقط
is actually pretty easy and pretty cheap,
هو في الواقع بسيط للغاية ورخيص للغاية،
not very cheap,
ليس رخيصا جدا،
but certainly less than the cost of a collapsing civilization.
لكنه بالتأكيد أقل من كلفة انهيار الحضارة.
We didn't calculate that precisely,
لم نحسب ذلك بدقة،
but we understand that's very expensive.
لكننا نفهم أن ذلك مكلف للغاية.
You can read the details,
يمكنكم قراءة التفاصيل،
but in summary, we can transform our economy.
لكن كخلاصة، يمكننا تحويل إقتصادنا.
We can do it with proven technology.
يمكننا القيام بذلك بتقنية مثبتة.
We can do it at an affordable cost.
يمكننا القيام بذلك بكلفة مناسبة.
We can do it with existing political structures.
يمكننا القيام بذلك ببنيات سياسية موجودة فعلاً.
The only thing we need to change
الأمر الوحيد الذي نحتاج تغييره
is how we think and how we feel.
هو كيف نفكر وكيف نشعر.
And this is where you come in.
وهنا دوركم
When we think about the future I paint,
حين أفكر في المستقبل أرسم،
of course we should feel a bit of fear.
بالطبع علينا أن نحس بنوع من الخوف.
But fear can be paralyzing or motivating.
لكن الخوف قد يكون مثبطاً او دافعاً.
We need to accept the fear and then we need to act.
علينا أن نتقبل الخوف ومن ثم نحتاج إلى التحرك.
We need to act
نحتاج للتحرك
like the future depends on it.
وكأن المستقبل يعتمد على ذلك.
We need to act like we only have one planet.
علينا أن نفكر أنه لدينا كوكب واحد فقط.
We can do this.
نستطيع القيام بهذا.
I know the free market fundamentalists will tell you
أعرف أن أصوليي السوق الحرة سيخبرونكم
that more growth, more stuff and nine billion people going shopping
أن مزيدا من النمو، المزيد من الأشياء وتسعة مليارات شخص يذهبون للتسوق
is the best we can do.
هو أفضل ما يمكن أن نقوم به.
They're wrong.
إنهم مخطئون.
We can be more,
نستطيع أن نكون أفضل
we can be much more.
نستطيع أن نكون أفضل بكثير.
We have achieved remarkable things
قد حققنا إنجازات عظيمة
since working out how to grow food some 10,000 years ago.
منذ معرفة كيفية زراعة الغذاء قبل حوالي 10,000 سنة.
We've built a powerful foundation
قد بنينا أساسا قويا
of science, knowledge and technology --
للعلم، المعرفة والتكنولوجيا --
more than enough to build a society
أكثر مما يكفي لبناء مجتمع
where nine billion people
حيث يمكن لتسعة مليارات شخص
can lead decent, meaningful and satisfying lives.
أن يعيشوا حياة كريمة ذات مغزى.
The Earth can support that
الأرض تستطيع تحمل ذلك
if we choose the right path.
إن اخترنا المسار الصحيح.
We can choose this moment of crisis
يمكن أن نختار لحظة الأزمة هاته
to ask and answer the big questions of society's evolution --
للتساؤل والإجابة عن أسئلة تطور المجتمع --
like, what do we want to be when we grow up,
مثل، ما الذي نريد أن نكونه حين نكبر،
when we move past this bumbling adolescence
حين نتجاوز هاته المراهقة المتلعثمة
where we think there are no limits
حيث نعتقد انه ليست هناك حدود
and suffer delusions of immortality?
ونعاني من وهم الخلود؟
Well it's time to grow up,
حسنا حان الوقت لننضج،
to be wiser, to be calmer,
لنكون أكثر حكمة ونكون أكثر هدوء،
to be more considered.
أن نكون أكثر اعتبارا.
Like generations before us,
مثل الأجيال قبلنا،
we'll be growing up in war --
سننضج في حرب --
not a war between civilizations,
ليست حربا بين الحضارات،
but a war for civilization,
لكن حرب الحضارة،
for the extraordinary opportunity
من أجل الفرصة المذهلة
to build a society
لبناء مجتمع
which is stronger and happier
أقوى وأسعد
and plans on staying around
ونخطط للبقاء
into middle age.
حتى العصور الوسطى.
We can choose life over fear.
نستطيع اختيار الحياة بدل الخوف.
We can do what we need to do,
يمكننا القيام بما نحتاج القيام به،
but it will take every entrepreneur,
لكن ذلك سيحتاج إلى كل مقاول،
every artist,
وكل فنان،
every scientist, every communicator,
وكل عالم، وكل متواصل،
every mother, every father, every child,
وكل أم، وكل أب، وكل طفل،
every one of us.
جميعنا.
This could be our finest hour.
هذه قد تكون أفضل الاوقات التي ستتاح لنا.
Thank you.
شكرا لكم.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)